<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2025//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_250101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>
<PubmedArticle><MedlineCitation Status="MEDLINE" Owner="NLM" IndexingMethod="Automated"><PMID Version="1">35041763</PMID><DateCompleted><Year>2022</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>08</Day></DateCompleted><DateRevised><Year>2022</Year><Month>06</Month><Day>29</Day></DateRevised><Article PubModel="Print"><Journal><ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1365-2133</ISSN><JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet"><Volume>186</Volume><Issue>6</Issue><PubDate><Year>2022</Year><Month>Jun</Month></PubDate></JournalIssue><Title>The British journal of dermatology</Title><ISOAbbreviation>Br J Dermatol</ISOAbbreviation></Journal><ArticleTitle>Mogamulizumab induces long-term immune restoration and reshapes tumour heterogeneity in S&#xe9;zary syndrome.</ArticleTitle><Pagination><StartPage>1010</StartPage><EndPage>1025</EndPage><MedlinePgn>1010-1025</MedlinePgn></Pagination><ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1111/bjd.21018</ELocationID><Abstract><AbstractText Label="BACKGROUND">Mogamulizumab, an anti-CCR4 monoclonal antibody, has been shown to increase progression-free survival in cutaneous T-cell lymphoma.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVES">We hypothesized that besides the targeted depletion of S&#xe9;zary cells (SCs), mogamulizumab may reshape the immune tumour microenvironment.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="METHODS">Both malignant and benign compartments from 26 patients with B2 stage S&#xe9;zary syndrome before mogamulizumab initiation were prospectively analysed using KIR3DL2 and TCRV&#x3b2; markers, serological markers and molecular assessments of clonality.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="RESULTS">Prior to mogamulizumab, the benign subset of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells displayed exhausted phenotypes, with an increased gradient in programmed death-1, TIGIT, DNAM-1, CD27, CD28 and CD70 expression from age-matched controls to patients' benign CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and to SCs. All patients presented SCs with heterogeneous phenotypes, and differential expression of individual markers was found within distinct malignant subsets. Early complete blood response was observed in 17 of 26 patients and was associated with higher baseline CCR4 expression. A drastic decrease in benign T cells and activated regulatory T-cell counts was observed during the first 4&#x2009;weeks. Long-term follow-up revealed the emergence of an immune restoration involving CD8<sup>+</sup> and naive and stem memory CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, with almost complete disappearance of exhausted lymphocytes. Development of resistance or tumour escape to mogamulizumab was associated with the emergence of CCR4<sup>-</sup> SCs in blood and skin, displaying significant changes in their heterogeneity patterns, and not explained only by mutations within CCR4 coding regions.</AbstractText><AbstractText Label="CONCLUSIONS">Mogamulizumab likely contributes to the restoration of efficient immunity and reshapes not only the malignant lymphocyte subset but also the benign subset. These results have potential implications for optimal therapeutic sequences and/or combinations. What is already known about this topic? Management of S&#xe9;zary syndrome (SS) involves successive therapies that participate as cause and consequence in the emergence of resistant clones, on a background of immunodeficiency. We and others have reported the complex and dynamic heterogeneity of S&#xe9;zary cells (SCs) during disease progression. Mogamulizumab therapy, by targeting the skin-homing receptor CCR4, mainly expressed by SCs, has been shown to increase progression-free survival in patients with SS. What does this study add? Using multicolour flow cytometry, we provide quantification of CCR4 and immune checkpoint molecules on malignant SCs and benign CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from patients with SS, separated using KIR3DL2 and TCRV&#x3b2; expression. Mogamulizumab is not only aimed at eradicating malignant SCs but potentially contributes to the restoration of efficient immunity. Tumour escape is associated with the emergence of CCR4<sup>-</sup> SCs, not explained only by mutations within CCR4 coding regions.</AbstractText><CopyrightInformation>&#xa9; 2022 British Association of Dermatologists.</CopyrightInformation></Abstract><AuthorList CompleteYN="Y"><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Roelens</LastName><ForeName>Marie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 1160.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>de Masson</LastName><ForeName>Ad&#xe8;le</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0001-7828-6211</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 976, Institut de Recherche Saint-Louis, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dermatology Department.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Andrillon</LastName><ForeName>Anais</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 1153.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Ram-Wolff</LastName><ForeName>Caroline</ForeName><Initials>C</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dermatology Department.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Biard</LastName><ForeName>Lucie</ForeName><Initials>L</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 1153.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Department of Biostatistics and Medical Information.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Boisson</LastName><ForeName>Marie</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tumor Genomics and Pharmacology Department.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Mourah</LastName><ForeName>Samia</ForeName><Initials>S</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 976, Institut de Recherche Saint-Louis, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Tumor Genomics and Pharmacology Department.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Battistella</LastName><ForeName>Maxime</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 976, Institut de Recherche Saint-Louis, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Pathology Department.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Toubert</LastName><ForeName>Antoine</ForeName><Initials>A</Initials><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 1160.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Immunology Laboratory.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Bagot</LastName><ForeName>Martine</ForeName><Initials>M</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0002-1631-5192</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 976, Institut de Recherche Saint-Louis, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Dermatology Department.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author><Author ValidYN="Y"><LastName>Moins-Teisserenc</LastName><ForeName>H&#xe9;l&#xe8;ne</ForeName><Initials>H</Initials><Identifier Source="ORCID">0000-0003-1602-7534</Identifier><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>INSERM UMR 1160.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Universit&#xe9; de Paris, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo><AffiliationInfo><Affiliation>Hematology Laboratory, H&#xf4;pital Saint-Louis, AP-HP, Paris, France.</Affiliation></AffiliationInfo></Author></AuthorList><Language>eng</Language><PublicationTypeList><PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType></PublicationTypeList></Article><MedlineJournalInfo><Country>England</Country><MedlineTA>Br J Dermatol</MedlineTA><NlmUniqueID>0004041</NlmUniqueID><ISSNLinking>0007-0963</ISSNLinking></MedlineJournalInfo><ChemicalList><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D061067">Antibodies, Monoclonal, Humanized</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>0</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="D054347">Receptors, KIR3DL2</NameOfSubstance></Chemical><Chemical><RegistryNumber>YI437801BE</RegistryNumber><NameOfSubstance UI="C549035">mogamulizumab</NameOfSubstance></Chemical></ChemicalList><CitationSubset>IM</CitationSubset><MeshHeadingList><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D061067" MajorTopicYN="N">Antibodies, Monoclonal, Humanized</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D006801" MajorTopicYN="N">Humans</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D000074243" MajorTopicYN="Y">Immune Reconstitution</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D016410" MajorTopicYN="Y">Lymphoma, T-Cell, Cutaneous</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000473" MajorTopicYN="N">pathology</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D054347" MajorTopicYN="N">Receptors, KIR3DL2</DescriptorName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012751" MajorTopicYN="Y">Sezary Syndrome</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D012878" MajorTopicYN="Y">Skin Neoplasms</DescriptorName><QualifierName UI="Q000188" MajorTopicYN="N">drug therapy</QualifierName><QualifierName UI="Q000235" MajorTopicYN="N">genetics</QualifierName></MeshHeading><MeshHeading><DescriptorName UI="D059016" MajorTopicYN="N">Tumor Microenvironment</DescriptorName></MeshHeading></MeshHeadingList></MedlineCitation><PubmedData><History><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised"><Year>2021</Year><Month>12</Month><Day>20</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received"><Year>2021</Year><Month>11</Month><Day>4</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>15</Day></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>19</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline"><Year>2022</Year><Month>6</Month><Day>9</Day><Hour>6</Hour><Minute>0</Minute></PubMedPubDate><PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez"><Year>2022</Year><Month>1</Month><Day>18</Day><Hour>17</Hour><Minute>27</Minute></PubMedPubDate></History><PublicationStatus>ppublish</PublicationStatus><ArticleIdList><ArticleId IdType="pubmed">35041763</ArticleId><ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1111/bjd.21018</ArticleId></ArticleIdList><ReferenceList><Title>References</Title><Reference><Citation>Nicolay JP, Felcht M, Schledzewski K et&#x2009;al. S&#xe9;zary syndrome: old enigmas, new targets. J Dtsch Dermatol Ges 2016; 14:256-64.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ferenczi K, Fuhlbrigge RC, Kupper TS et&#x2009;al. Increased CCR4 expression in cutaneous T cell lymphoma. J Invest Dermatol 2002; 119:1405-10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sugaya M, Morimura S, Suga H et&#x2009;al. CCR4 is expressed on infiltrating cells in lesional skin of early mycosis fungoides and atopic dermatitis. J Dermatol 2015; 42:613-15.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kim YH, Bagot M, Pinter-Brown L et&#x2009;al. Mogamulizumab versus vorinostat in previously treated cutaneous T-cell lymphoma (MAVORIC): an international, open-label, randomised, controlled phase 3 trial. Lancet Oncol 2018; 19:1192-204.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Iellem A, Mariani M, Lang R et&#x2009;al. Unique chemotactic response profile and specific expression of chemokine receptors Ccr4 and Ccr8 by Cd4+Cd25+ regulatory T cells. J Exp Med 2001; 194:847-54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bonnet P, Battistella M, Roelens M et&#x2009;al. Association of autoimmunity and long-term complete remission in patients with S&#xe9;zary syndrome treated with mogamulizumab. Br J Dermatol 2019; 180:419-20.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trager M, Clippel&#xe9; D, Ram-Wolff C et&#x2009;al. Mogamulizumab-induced mucocutaneous lichenoid reaction: a case report and short review. Acta Derm Venereol 2020; 100:adv00158.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Algarni AS, Ram-Wolff C, Bagot M, de Masson A. Mogamulizumab-induced vitiligo in patients with S&#xe9;zary syndrome: three cases. Eur J Dermatol 2021; 31:213-16.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang JY, Hirotsu KE, Neal TM et&#x2009;al. Histopathologic characterization of mogamulizumab-associated rash. Am J Surg Pathol 2020; 44:1666-76.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hirotsu KE, Neal TM, Khodadoust MS et&#x2009;al. Clinical characterization of mogamulizumab-associated rash during treatment of mycosis fungoides or S&#xe9;zary syndrome. JAMA Dermatol 2021; 157:700.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Musiek ACM, Rieger KE, Bagot M et&#x2009;al. Dermatologic events associated with the anti-CCR4 antibody mogamulizumab: characterization and management. Dermatol Ther (Heidelb) 2022; 12:29-40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Trum NA, Zain J, Martinez XU et&#x2009;al. Mogamulizumab efficacy is underscored by its associated rash that mimics cutaneous T-cell lymphoma: a retrospective single-centre case series. Br J Dermatol 2022; 186:153-66.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>de Masson A, Darbord D, Dobos G et&#x2009;al. Macrophage-derived CXCL9 and CXCL11, T-cell skin homing and disease control in mogamulizumab-treated CTCL patients. Blood 2022; 139:1820-32.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Tanaka A, Sakaguchi S. Regulatory T cells in cancer immunotherapy. Cell Res 2017; 27:109-18.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Olsen EA, Whittaker S, Kim YH et&#x2009;al. Clinical end points and response criteria in mycosis fungoides and S&#xe9;zary syndrome: a consensus statement of the International Society for Cutaneous Lymphomas, the United States Cutaneous Lymphoma Consortium, and the Cutaneous Lymphoma Task Force of the European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer. J Clin Oncol 2011; 29:2598-607.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Scarisbrick JJ, Hodak E, Bagot M et&#x2009;al. Blood classification and blood response criteria in mycosis fungoides and S&#xe9;zary syndrome using flow cytometry: recommendations from the EORTC cutaneous lymphoma task force. Eur J Cancer 2018; 93:47-56.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Moins-Teisserenc H, Daubord M, Clave E et&#x2009;al. CD158k is a reliable marker for diagnosis of S&#xe9;zary syndrome and reveals an unprecedented heterogeneity of circulating malignant cells. J Invest Dermatol 2015; 135:247-57.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Anzengruber F, Ignatova D, Schlaepfer T et&#x2009;al. Divergent LAG-3 versus BTLA, TIGIT, and FCRL3 expression in S&#xe9;zary syndrome. Leuk Lymphoma 2019; 60:1899-907.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Jacobs J, Deschoolmeester V, Zwaenepoel K et&#x2009;al. CD70: an emerging target in cancer immunotherapy. Pharmacol Ther 2015; 155:1-10.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Bagot M, Maerevoet M, Zinzani PL et&#x2009;al. Argx-110 for treatment of CD70-positive advanced cutaneous T-cell lymphoma in a phase 1/2 clinical trial. Blood 2018; 132 (Suppl. 1):1627.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Hafler DA, Lozano E, Dominguez-Villar M, Kuchroo V. Cell function the TIGIT/CD226 axis regulates human T cell function. J Immunol 2021; 188:3869-75.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Vergnolle I, Douat-Beyries C, Boulinguez S et&#x2009;al. CD158k and PD-1 expressions define heterogeneous subtypes of S&#xe9;zary syndrome. Blood Adv 2022; 6:1813-25.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Querfeld C, Leung S, Myskowski PL et&#x2009;al. Primary T cells from cutaneous T-cell lymphoma skin explants display an exhausted immune checkpoint profile. Cancer Immunol Res 2018; 6:900-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kasakovski D, Xu L, Li Y. T cell senescence and CAR-T cell exhaustion in hematological malignancies. J Hematol Oncol 2018; 11:91.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Roelens M, Delord M, Ram-Wolff C et&#x2009;al. Circulating and skin-derived S&#xe9;zary cells: clonal but with phenotypic plasticity. Blood 2017; 130:1468-71.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Buus TB, Willerslev-Olsen A, Fredholm S et&#x2009;al. Single-cell heterogeneity in S&#xe9;zary syndrome. Blood Adv 2018; 2:2115-26.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Borcherding N, Voigt AP, Liu V et&#x2009;al. Single-cell profiling of cutaneous T-cell lymphoma reveals underlying heterogeneity associated with disease progression. Cancer Clin Res 2019; 25:2996-3005.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Gaydosik AM, Tabib T, Geskin LJ et&#x2009;al. Single-cell lymphocyte heterogeneity in advanced cutaneous T-cell lymphoma skin tumors. Cancer Clin Res 2019; 25:4443-54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Najidh S, Tensen CP, van der Sluijs-Gelling AJ et&#x2009;al. Improved S&#xe9;zary cell detection and novel insights into immunophenotypic and molecular heterogeneity in S&#xe9;zary syndrome. Blood 2021; 138:2539-54.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Wang L, Ni X, Covington KR et&#x2009;al. Genomic profiling of S&#xe9;zary syndrome identifies alterations of key T cell signaling and differentiation genes. Nat Genet 2015; 47:1426-34.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ni X, Jorgensen JL, Goswami M et&#x2009;al. Reduction of regulatory T cells by mogamulizumab, a defucosylated anti-CC chemokine receptor 4 antibody, in patients with aggressive/refractory mycosis fungoides and S&#xe9;zary syndrome. Cancer Clin Res 2015; 21:274-85.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Miller I, Min M, Yang C et&#x2009;al. Ki67 is a graded rather than a binary marker of proliferation versus quiescence. Cell Rep 2018; 24:1105-12.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Rochman Y, Spolski R, Leonard WJ. New insights into the regulation of T cells by &#x3b3;c family cytokines. Nat Rev Immunol 2009; 9:480-90.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Sakamoto Y, Ishida T, Masaki A et&#x2009;al. CCR4 mutations associated with superior outcome of adult T-cell leukemia/lymphoma under mogamulizumab treatment. Blood 2018; 132:758-61.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Ohno N, Kobayashi S, Ishigaki T et&#x2009;al. Loss of CCR4 antigen expression after mogamulizumab therapy in a case of adult T-cell leukaemia-lymphoma. Br J Haematol 2013; 163:683-5.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Cook LBM, Demontis MA, Sagawe S et&#x2009;al. Molecular remissions are observed in chronic adult T-cell leukemia/lymphoma in patients treated with mogamulizumab. Haematologica 2019; 104:e566-9.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Mariani M, Lang R, Binda E et&#x2009;al. Dominance of CCL22 over CCL17 in induction of chemokine receptor CCR4 desensitization and internalization on human Th2 cells. Eur J Immunol 2004; 34:231-40.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Kitadate A, Ikeda S, Abe F et&#x2009;al. Histone deacetylase inhibitors downregulate CCR4 expression and decrease mogamulizumab efficacy in CCR4-positive mature T-cell lymphomas. Haematologica 2018; 103:126-35.</Citation></Reference><Reference><Citation>Abe F, Kitadate A, Ikeda S et&#x2009;al. Histone deacetylase inhibitors inhibit metastasis by restoring a tumor suppressive microRNA-150 in advanced cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. Oncotarget 2017; 8:7572-85.</Citation></Reference></ReferenceList></PubmedData></PubmedArticle></PubmedArticleSet>