<?xml version="1.0"  ?><!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd"><pmc-articleset><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.4"><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Immunother Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Immunother Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">2348</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">jimmthercanc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jitc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal for Immunotherapy of Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2051-1426</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11907075</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid-ver">PMC11907075.1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">11907075</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">11907075</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">40081941</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jitc-2024-010959</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jitc-2024-010959</article-id><article-version article-version-type="pmc-version">1</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Cancer Immunotherapy</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>2435</subject><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Myeloid targeting antibodies PY159 and PY314 for platinum-resistant ovarian cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6319-1647</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Yeku</surname><given-names initials="OO">Oladapo O</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Barve</surname><given-names initials="M">Minal</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tan</surname><given-names initials="WW">Winston W</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names initials="J">Judy</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names initials="A">Amita</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>LoRusso</surname><given-names initials="P">Patricia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3992-8610</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names initials="DL">Debra L</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">7</xref><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naqash</surname><given-names initials="AR">Abdul Rafeh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">9</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lynam</surname><given-names initials="SK">Sarah K</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu</surname><given-names initials="S">Siqing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names initials="M">Michael</given-names></name><xref rid="aff12" ref-type="aff">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names initials="J">Joleen</given-names></name><xref rid="aff13" ref-type="aff">13</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kummar</surname><given-names initials="S">Shivaani</given-names></name><xref rid="aff14" ref-type="aff">14</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6452-7405</contrib-id><name name-style="western"><surname>Kyriakopoulos</surname><given-names initials="C">Christos</given-names></name><xref rid="aff15" ref-type="aff">15</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dowlati</surname><given-names initials="A">Afshin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">10</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chamberlain</surname><given-names initials="M">Marc</given-names></name><xref rid="aff16" ref-type="aff">16</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winer</surname><given-names initials="I">Ira</given-names></name><xref rid="aff17" ref-type="aff">17</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="department">Medicine/Cancer Center</institution>, <institution>Massachusetts General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Boston</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Massachusetts</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Mary Crowley Cancer Research</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Dallas</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Texas</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Mayo Clinic</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Jackson</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Florida</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><label>4</label><institution content-type="department">Drug Development Unit</institution>, <institution>Florida Cancer Specialists/Sarah Cannon Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Sarasota</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Florida</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><label>5</label><institution>The START Center for Cancer Research</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Antonio</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Texas</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><label>6</label><institution>Yale University Yale Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">New Haven</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Connecticut</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff7"><label>7</label><institution content-type="department">Division of Gynecologic Oncology</institution>, <institution>The University of Oklahoma Stephenson Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Oklahoma City</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Oklahoma</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff8"><label>8</label><institution>Sarah Cannon Research Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Oklahoma City</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Oklahoma</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff9"><label>9</label><institution content-type="department">Medical Oncology/TSET Phase 1 Program</institution>, <institution>Stephenson Cancer Center/Sarah Cannon Research Institute, University of Oklahoma Health Sciences Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Oklahoma City</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Oklahoma</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff10"><label>10</label><institution>University Hospitals Seidman Cancer Center and Case Western Reserve University</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Ohio</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff11"><label>11</label><institution>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Houston</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Texas</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff12"><label>12</label><institution>HonorHealth</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Scottsdale</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Arizona</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff13"><label>13</label><institution>Allina Health Cancer Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Minneapolis</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Minnesota</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff14"><label>14</label><institution>Oregon Health &amp; Science University Knight Cancer Institute</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Portland</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Oregon</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff15"><label>15</label><institution content-type="department">Medicine, Hematology/Oncology</institution>, <institution>University of Wisconsin</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Madison</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Wisconsin</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff16"><label>16</label><institution>Pionyr Immunotherapeutics</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">South San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff17"><label>17</label><institution>Wayne State University and Karmanos Cancer Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Detroit</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Michigan</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p>Supplemental material This content has been supplied by the author(s). It has not been vetted by BMJ Publishing Group Limited (BMJ) and may not have been peer-reviewed. Any opinions or recommendations discussed are solely those of the author(s) and are not endorsed by BMJ. BMJ disclaims all liability and responsibility arising from any reliance placed on the content. Where the content includes any translated material, BMJ does not warrant the accuracy and reliability of the translations (including but not limited to local regulations, clinical guidelines, terminology, drug names and drug dosages), and is not responsible for any error and/or omissions arising from translation and adaptation or otherwise.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Additional supplemental material is published online only. To view, please visit the journal online (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1136/jitc-2024-010959" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1136/jitc-2024-010959</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="fn5"><p>O.O.Y reports grants from Ascendis Pharma A/S, Avenge Bio, Inc., Immunocore Limited, Duality Biologics, Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme Corporation, Pionyr Immunotherapeutics Inc., ProfoundBio, and the Department of Defense. Consulting fees from Celldex Therapeutics, GIMV NV, TigaTx Inc. Advisory board role at hC Bioscience. In addition, he has a patent pending for MUC16 Directed Antibodies for therapeutic applications, and a patent pending for Human Artificial Chromosomes for therapeutic applications. M.B. reports stock ownership in Texas Oncology, Funding from I-Mab, and Tempus. A.P reports honoraria from Texas Society of Clinical Oncology. Consulting fees paid to an immediate family member from Genentech/Roche, Merck. Consulting fees from Bayer, Novartis, Merck, Seagen, Silverback Therapeutics, Shenzhen Ionova life sciences Co., Ltd, Gilead Sciences, Daiichi Sankyo, Inc, Halio Dx, Janssen, Loxo, Pfzer, Quanta Therapeutics, Pfizer. D.R reports research funding from GSK. Advisory boards for Mersana, Immunogen, GSK, AstraZeneca, Eisai, Daiichi Sankyo, Repare Therapeutics, Profound Bio and Incyclix Bio. Speaking engagement for Zentalis. A.V.N reports consultant editor compensation from JCO Precision Oncology, travel compensation from SITC, AACR, Conquer Cancer Foundation, BinayTara Foundation, Foundation medicine, Caris Life Sciences, ASCO. Advisory Board compensation from Foundation Medicine, Astellas, and NGM. Honoraria from BinayTara Foundation, Foundation Medicine, Medlive and grant Support from SOWG Hope Foundation. M.M.G reports grants from GSK, Abbvie, Merck Serono, Medimmune, Incyte, Pfizer, Amgen, Gilead Sciences, Endocyte, Seattle Genetics, Plexxicon/Daiichi, Celldex, Tracon, Deciphera, Fujifilm, Minnemarita, Nektar, Novita, Biosplice, Corcept, Novartis, Toray, Genzada, Salarius, Agenus, Inhibrx, AADI, Revolution Medicine, Blueprint, Astellas, BioNTech, Helix, IgM Biosciences, ImmuneSensor, Bioeclipse, Bioline, Black Diamond, Codiak, Dracen, Elevation Oncology, Famewave, Forma Therapeutics, IntraImmun SG, Pionyr, Trishula, Tolero, Vedanta Biosciences, Coordination Therapeutics, Ideaya Biosciences, I-Mab, NiKang, Nimbus Therapeutics, OncoResponse, Riboscience, Rubius Therapeutics, Simcha Therapeutics, Siranomics, Synthorx, Theseus Pharmaceuticals, Zai Labs, Adanate, Fog Pharma, PEEL, Orionis, SQZ, YMABS, Iovance, Vincerx, Werewolf, Adaptimmune, Alyssum, Apros, CG Pharmaceutical, Bright Peak, Dynamicure, Elpiscience, Iovance, Flare, Georgiamune, IDEAYA, Immuneering, Krystal Biotech, Medical College of Wisconsin, Perspective Therapeutics, Profound Bio, Pyxis, Qualigen, Springworks Therapeutics, Storm Therapeutics, TSCAN, Syndax, Vincerx, Werewolf Therapeutics, Beigene, Incyte, RedHill, Veru, Syndax. Consulting fees from; Pfizer, Imaging Endpoints, Curio. Honoraria from Lisa Stearns Academy. Patents issued or pending from Sphinx Health Solutions. Advisory board participation with Daiichi, Qualigen, Springworks, Cardinal Healthcare, IQVIA, Medtronics, Deciphera. J.H reports consulting fees from Bayer, Taiho Oncology. Institutional research funding from BeiGene, Taiho Pharmaceutical, Treos Bio, Seagen, Trovagene, Incyte, Pionyr, G1 Therapeutics, and Pfizer. A.D reports Advisory board participation on Advisory Boards: Astra Zeneca, Amgen, Jazz, Prelude, PUMA, Abbvie. No other disclosures were reported by the other authors. J.S.W reports consulting fees from Kanaph Therapeutics, Fusion Pharmaceuticals. Speakers’ bureau from AstraZeneca and Eisai. S.K reports Consultant/Advisory board positions at: Springworks Therapeutics, SeaGen, Bayer, Genome &amp; Company, HarbourBiomed, BPGbio Therapeutics, Oxford Biotherapeutics, Mundibiopharma, BPGbio, Inc., Gilead, Mirati; Fortress Biotech, Inc, GI Innovation Inc, XYone Therapeutics, Genome Insight, Aadi Biosciences, MOMA Therapeutics, Daiichi Sankyo PathomIQ (co-founder), Cadila Pharmaceuticals (scientific advisor-spouse), and Arxeon (co-founder-spouse).</p></fn><corresp id="cor1">DrIraWiner; <email xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="iwiner@med.wayne.edu">iwiner@med.wayne.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="pmc-issue-id">483378</issue-id><elocation-id>e010959</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>05</day><month>11</month><year>2024</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>2</month><year>2025</year></date></history><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>13</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-live"><date><day>14</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event><event event-type="pmc-last-change"><date iso-8601-date="2025-03-15 10:26:04.270"><day>15</day><month>03</month><year>2025</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © Author(s) (or their employer(s)) 2025. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbynclicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited, appropriate credit is given, any changes made indicated, and the use is non-commercial. See <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="pmc-pdf" xlink:href="jitc-13-3.pdf"/><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="jitc-13-3.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec><title>Background</title><p>Novel treatment options are required in patients with platinum-resistant ovarian cancer (PROC). Myeloid-derived suppressor cells promote a hostile tumor microenvironment and are associated with worse clinical outcomes in PROC. We evaluated the safety and preliminary efficacy of PY159, an agonist antibody to Triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells-1 (TREM1) that reprograms immunosuppressive intratumoral myeloid cells, and PY314, an antagonist antibody to Triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells-2 (TREM2) that depletes tumor-associated macrophages, as single agents and in combination with pembrolizumab in subjects with PROC.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>PY159 and PY314 were individually evaluated in patients with PROC. Patients were treated with monotherapy (PY159 3 mg/kg or PY314 10 mg/kg), based on the recommended dose for expansion derived from the phase 1a studies. At the time of first progression, patients could continue study drug and crossover to combination therapy with pembrolizumab (200 mg) every 3 weeks at the discretion of the investigator. Disease assessment by Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumor version 1.1 was performed every 6 weeks.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>17 patients were enrolled in the PY159 study (median age 67, range 22–77; median prior therapies 6, range 2–18) and 16 patients in PY314 (median age 65.5, range 49–81; median prior therapies 4, range 2–10). 7 patients in PY159 and 8 patients in PY314 crossed over to combination therapy. Safety events included the following: treatment-related adverse events occurred in 15 patients (88.2%) in PY159 and 9 patients (56.3%) in PY314. Infusion-related reactions occurred in 6 patients (35.3%) in PY159 and 3 patients (18.8%) in PY314. Immune-related adverse events occurred in 13 patients (76.5%) in PY159 (arthralgias) and 1 patient (6.3%) in PY314 (diarrhea). Serious adverse events occurred in 6 patients (36.3%) in PY159 (1 related) and 12 patients (75%) in PY314 (all unrelated). The best radiographic response in PY159 was stable disease in 8/16 patients (50%; median 16 weeks, range 9–33), and in PY314, it was stable disease in 8/16 patients (50%; median 12 weeks, range 6–36). Median PFS was 2.76 months and 2.69 months in PY159 and PY314, respectively. There were no responses in the crossover arm.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Both PY159 and PY314 were well tolerated, with an acceptable safety profile, as both single agents and in combination with pembrolizumab. Both agents warrant further investigation in heavily pretreated PROC.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ovarian Cancer</kwd><kwd>Tumor Microenvironment</kwd><kwd>Antibody</kwd><kwd>Immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>Myeloid-derived suppressor cell - MDSC</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Pionyr Immunotherapeutics</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>N/A</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-qastatus</meta-name><meta-value>0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-live</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-embargo</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-status-released</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-open-access</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-legally-suppressed</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-has-supplement</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-pdf-only</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-suppress-copyright</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-real-version</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-is-scanned-article</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-prop-in-epmc</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>pmc-license-ref</meta-name><meta-value>CC BY-NC</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><boxed-text id="BWL1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>WHAT IS ALREADY KNOWN ABOUT THIS TOPIC</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>There is an urgent and unmet need for efficacious and tolerable treatment options for platinum -resistant ovarian cancer.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Immune checkpoint inhibitors have shown limited efficacy in ovarian cancer, partly due to a hostile tumor microenvironment that suppresses the activity of cytotoxic immune engagers.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Murine models and translational data have shown a detrimental effect of tumor -associated macrophages (TAMs) and myeloid -derived suppressor cells (MDSCs) and either depletion or reprogramming of these cells haves led to improved outcomes in experimental models.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>WHAT THIS STUDY ADDS</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>We aimed to test the hypothesis that either repolarizing TAMs or MDSCs towards a more inflammatory phenotype or depleting them from the tumor microenvironment would improve outcomes in platinum -resistant ovarian cancer. We evaluated PY159, a monoclonal antibody that binds to TREM1 expressed on TAMs and MDSCs leading to repolarization towards an inflammatory and anti-tumor phenotype, and PY314, a monoclonal antibody that binds to TREM2 on TAMs leading to depletion in the tumor microenvironment in a phase 1 clinical trial. PY159 and PY314 were evaluated in two independent studies as monotherapy or in combination with pembrolizumab on disease progression.</p></list-item><list-item><p>PY159 and PY314 were well tolerated, and immune -related adverse events were mitigated with glucocorticoids. Both PY159 and PY314 led to stable disease in platinum -resistant ovarian cancer.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><boxed-text id="BWL2" position="float" orientation="portrait"><sec><title>HOW THIS STUDY MIGHT AFFECT RESEARCH, PRACTICE OR POLICY</title><list list-type="bullet" list-content="ul"><list-item><p>This study provides clinical proof of concept for TAM and MDSC modulation in a heavily pretreated population of patients with platinum -resistant ovarian cancer. The mechanisms of action and side effect profiles of PY159 and PY314 lends itself to combination therapy with cytotoxic chemotherapy or immunotherapy which could be explored in future clinical trials.</p></list-item></list></sec></boxed-text><sec sec-type="background" id="s1"><title>Background</title><p> In 2023, there were estimated to be ~19 000 new cases of ovarian cancer diagnosed and ~13 000 deaths from this disease.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> For high-grade ovarian cancer (HG-OVCA), about 80% of patient respond to standard therapy with carboplatin and taxanes in the upfront setting; however, about 20% are platinum refractory (ie, progressive disease on upfront therapy) at diagnosis. Additionally, most patients will recur within 2 years of primary treatment even with newer maintenance strategies, with many becoming platinum resistant at first or second recurrence.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 3</sup></xref> Once platinum resistance has developed, overall response rates to chemotherapy are generally in the 10%–30% range and decrease progressively over time. Overall survival is generally 1–2 years once a patient becomes platinum resistant.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2 4</sup></xref> The only significant advance in this treatment setting in over a decade was the antibody drug conjugate mirvetuximab soravtansine which improved median overall survival by about 4 months compared with chemotherapy.<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Given this, newer treatments are needed. One significant area of investigation has been the tumor microenvironment (TME) and specifically targeting pathways leading to immune evasion. Historically, monotherapy responses to immune checkpoint inhibitors are 10%–15% in OVCA with many studies currently examining a broad range of monotherapy and combination therapies but still with lower than anticipated responses.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6 7</sup></xref></p><p>Recently, there has been significant interest in investigation of the myeloid lineages, their interactions with the TME, and the mechanisms whereby this leads to resistance to both conventional and targeted therapies including immuno-oncology (IO) agents.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref> PY159 and PY314 are being developed in this space.</p><p>PY159 is an agonist afucosylated humanized monoclonal antibody (mAb) that binds to triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells-1 (TREM1), a member of the immunoglobulin variable domain receptor superfamily. This receptor is expressed primarily on neutrophils, monocyte subsets, and tissue macrophages, as well as intratumoral immunosuppressive myeloid cells, including tumor-associated macrophages (TAMs), monocytic myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs), and tumor-associated neutrophils. Binding leads to a proinflammatory state and promotion of antitumor immune responses.<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></p><p>PY314 is a separate, antagonistic, humanized afucosylated glycoengineered IgG1κ mAB targeting triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells-2 (TREM2), a transmembrane protein expressed on a subset of myeloid cells and enriched on myeloid suppressive cells, particularly M2-like anti-inflammatory TAMs. In this case, antagonism of the TREM2 receptor leads to depletion of suppressive TAMs within the TME and creates a similar proinflammatory state with promotion of antitumor immune response as with PY159.<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></p><p>Both agents were investigated in separate phase IA dose escalation studies as well as dose expansion phase IB cohorts. The recommended phase 2 doses of PY159<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> and PY314<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> were established in their individual dose-escalation studies based on safety, receptor occupancy, and in vitro cytotoxicity assays. This report documents the outcomes of these two distinct trials in patients with HG-serous OVCA.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Patients and methods</title><p>A total of 17 patients were enrolled to the ovarian cancer expansion cohort for PY159 and 1 patient withdrew consent due to toxicity during cycle 1. All 17 patients were included in safety analysis and 16 patients were included in the efficacy analysis. In the PY314 monotherapy expansion cohort, 16 patients were enrolled. Three patients withdrew their consent, 1 withdrew due to fistula unrealted to therapy, 2 withdrew for adverse events. All 16 patients were included in the safety and efficacy analysis. 11 sites in the USA participated in the trial. Inclusion criteria for study entry included adults greater than 18 years of age, an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status of 0–2, histologically proven epithelial ovarian, fallopian tube or primary peritoneal carcinoma, provision of an archival and fresh biopsy tumor samples for TREM1 or TREM2 immunohistochemistry analysis, documented disease progression on standard of care therapies with known platinum resistance, Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumor version 1.1 (RECIST 1.1) measurable disease, absence of brain metastases, no autoimmune disease requiring disease-modifying therapy, resolution of prior treatment-related toxicity to Grade 1 or less (Grade 2 allowed for alopecia, endocrinopathies on replacement hormone therapy, and peripheral neuropathy), normal organ function, estimated life expectancy greater than 3 months, no recent surgery (28 days interval for major and 7 days for a minor surgery from time to first dose), and no limit on prior therapies. Exclusion criteria included patients with germ cell, stromal cell, neuroendocrine or carcinosarcoma histology, uncontrolled intercurrent illness, decompensated liver disease as evidenced by hepatic encephalopathy or coagulopathy, active angina or Class III or IV CHF (NYHA CHF Functional Classification System) or clinically significant cardiac disease within 12 months of first dose of study drug, any anticancer therapy within 21 days (dependent on the agent and drug half-life), of first dose of study drug, history of a concurrent or second malignancy, known HIV infection or AIDS, known positive hepatitis B surface antigen test, known positive hepatitis C antibody test, history of long QT syndrome or whose corrected QT interval (QTc) measured (Fridericia method) at screening is prolonged (&gt;500 milliseconds), active infection requiring treatment within 7 days prior to first dose of study drug, and history or evidence of clinically significant disorder, condition, or disease that, in the opinion of the investigator or medical monitor would pose a risk to patient safety or interfere with the study evaluations, procedures, or study completion.</p><sec id="s2-1"><title>Study procedures</title><p>Both studies received approval from the Institutional Review Boards of the respective institutions. All participants gave consent to participate. All patients for the dose expansion cohorts of PY159 and PY314 signed informed consent for study participation. The recommended phase 2 dose of PY159 was determined to be 3 mg/kg on day 1, administered as an intravenous infusion over 30 min with premedication to mitigate infusion-related reactions every 21 days. In a separate dose escalation study, the recommended phase 2 dosing of PY314 was declared as 3 mg/kg on day 1, administered as an intravenous infusion over 30 min without premedication every 21 days. During the 28-day screening window, patients underwent a laboratory assessment for eligibility as well as a contrast CT of the chest, abdomen, and pelvis to determine RECIST 1.1 defined target and non-target lesions. Following review of protocol-mandated studies obtained during screening, patients enrolled in the ovarian cancer expansion cohorts of the respective trials. The cycle length was 21 days and response assessment was performed once every 42 days. Patients with stable or an objective radiographic response continued treatment as tolerated until disease progression, toxicity, or consent withdrawal. Patients with progression of disease at first assessment were eligible to cross over to combination therapy with pembrolizumab if deemed appropriate by the treating investigator. In patients who crossed over in the respective PY159 and PY314 studies, pembrolizumab was administered 30 min after PY159 or PY314 at a fixed dose of 200 mg over 30 min infusion every 3 weeks.</p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Study endpoints</title><p>The primary endpoints of both PY159 and PY314 expansion cohorts were to determine the incidence of adverse events (AEs) alone and in combination with pembrolizumab for patients who crossed over to the combination cohorts; identified as safe, tolerable, and providing target therapeutic exposure. Secondary endpoints included determining the pharmacokinetic (PK) profile of PY159 and PY314 as measured by standard PK parameters, measures of antitumor activity/disease status from baseline including objective response rate (ORR), clinical benefit rate (CBR), and duration of response (DOR) as defined by RECIST 1.1, and the incidence of antidrug antibody formation. Exploratory endpoints were identification of TREM1 and TREM2 in archival tissue, pre-treatment biopsies, and on-treatment biopsies by protein expression as determined by immunohistochemistry using proprietary anti-TREM1 or anti-TREM2 monoclonal antibodies. Expression was determined by a manual scoring system wherein the percent of macrophages and neutrophils staining for TREM1 or TREM2 in the tumor intervening stroma per the total number of cells (both stromal and tumor) was calculated.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>There were no formal statistical hypotheses or sample-size calculations for the ovarian cancer dose expansion cohorts for PY159 or PY314. Descriptive statistics were used throughout. Efficacy variables were analyzed in the intention-to-treat population (all enrolled patients). Time-to-event parameters were analyzed using descriptive and Kaplan-Meier statistics. Categorical variables were summarized by frequency distributions and continuous variables were summarized by descriptive statistics.</p><p>Safety data was analyzed for all patients who received at least 1 dose of PY159 or PY314. Adverse events were summarized by Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) system organ class and preferred term. All AEs were classified according to the National Cancer Institute CTCAE version 5.0. Separate tabulations were produced for all treatment-emergent AEs (TEAEs), treatment-related AEs (TRAEs; those considered by the investigator as at least possibly drug related), serious adverse events (SAEs), discontinuations due to AEs, and AEs of at least CTCAE Grade 3 severity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3-1"><title>Patients and demographics</title><p>From February 2022 to November 2022, a total of 17 patients and 16 patients were enrolled to the expansion cohorts of PY159 and PY314, respectively. The characteristics of enrolled patients in both trials are shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. The median age of patients in the PY159 and PY314 studies was 67 years (range, 22–77) and 65.5 years (49 – 81) respectively. 15 (88.2%) and 12 (75%) patients enrolled to PY159 and PY314 identified as white non-Hispanic, respectively. The median number of prior lines of treatment in PY159 was 6 (range, 2–18) and 4 (2 – 10) in PY314. In PY159 and PY314, 16 (94.1%) and 15 (93.7%) patients had received more than three prior lines of cytotoxic therapy, and all were platinum resistant. In the PY159 expansion study, 12 (58.8%) had received prior bevacizumab, 11 (64.7%) had received a prior PARP inhibitor, and 4 (23.5%) had been previously treated with an immune checkpoint inhibitor. In the PY314 expansion study, 12 (75%) patients had previously received bevacizumab, 6 (37.5%) had received a PARP, and 7 (43.8%) had been previously treated with an immune checkpoint inhibitor. There were 6 (35.3%) and 2 (12.5%) patients with BRCA or Homologous Deficiency Repair pathway mutations in PY159 and PY314 respectively.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Summary of baseline characteristics from PY159 and PY314 ovarian cancer cohorts</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PY159(n=17)</td><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PY314(n=16)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Age—years</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Median (range)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (22–77)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.5 (49–81)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;50</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.9%)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.3%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> 50–65</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (29.4%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (43.8%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥65</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (64.7%)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (50.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Race</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Asian</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.3%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Black</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.9%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Other</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.3%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> White</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (88.2%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (75.0%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Prior lines</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Median (range)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (2–18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (2–10)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> &lt;3</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (5.9%)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.3%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> ≥3</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (94.1%)</td><td valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (93.7%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Prior bevacizumab</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (58.8%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (75%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (17.6%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (25%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (23.5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Prior immune checkpoint inhibitor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (23.5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (43.8%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (76.5%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (56.2%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Prior PARP inhibitor</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Yes</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (64.7%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (37.5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> No</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (35.3%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (50%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.0%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12.5%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Mutational status</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> BRCA1/2 mut</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.6%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.3%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> HRD/LOH</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6.3%)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (17.6%)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12.5%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>HRDhomologous recombination deficiencyLOHloss of heterozygosity</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-2"><title>Response</title><p>The best radiographic response observed with either PY159 or PY314 was stable disease. Of the 16 evaluable patients in PY159, 8 (50%) patients had stable disease with a median duration of 16 weeks (range, 9–33) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1A,B</xref>). At the time of study termination, 2 patients remained on treatment. The median PFS for patients in the PY159 expansion study was 2.76 months (95% CI, 1.35 to 5.32). In PY314, 16 patients were evaluable for response. Eight (50%) patients had stable disease with a median duration of response of 12 weeks (range, 6–36 weeks) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">figure 1C,D</xref>). One patient remained on treatment at study termination. The median PFS for patients treated with PY314 was 2.69 months (95% CI, 1.18 to 4.07).</p><fig position="float" id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Response assessments after treatment with PY159 or PY314 in the dose expansion cohorts. (<bold>A</bold>) Waterfall plot and (<bold>B</bold>) swimmer’s plot depicting duration of response for all evaluable patients treated in the expansion cohort of PY159. (<bold>C</bold>) Waterfall plot and (<bold>D</bold>) swimmer’s plot depicting duration of response for all evaluable patients treated in the expansion cohort of PY314.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jitc-13-3-g001.jpg"/></fig><p>At first progression, 7 patients in the PY159 expansion cohort crossed over to combination therapy with pembrolizumab. There were no objective responses in the crossover cohort and all 7 patients progressed, although 2 of these 7 patients achieved stable disease past progression. The median time to second progression was 3 weeks (range, 3–15 weeks). Eight patients on the PY314 study crossed over to pembrolizumab combination at first progression. There were no objective responses although stabilization of disease occurred in 5 of these 8 patients. The median time to second progression was 6 weeks (range, 3–27 weeks).</p></sec><sec id="s3-3"><title>Adverse Events</title><sec id="s3-3-1"><title>PY159</title><p>All 17 (100%) patients had at least one TEAE of Grade 1 or 2. Grade 3 TEAEs occurred in 8 (47.1%) patients. The most common TEAEs occurring in &gt;15% of patients are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2A</xref> and <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 1</xref>. TRAEs occurred in 15 (88.2%) patients. TRAEs occurring in &gt;10% of patients are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2B</xref> and <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>. Grade 1 or 2 TRAEs occurred in 13 (76.5%) and Grade 3 events occurred in 2 (11.8%) patients. SAEs occurred in 6 (35.3%) patients, with Grade 1 and 2 events occurring in 2 (11.8%) patients and Grade 3 events in 3 patients (17.6%). There was 1 fatal adverse event of pericardial effusion unrelated to PY159. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows a list of SAEs and immune-related adverse events (irAEs). Arthralgias, stomatitis, and myalgia were irAEs of special interest, occurring in 13 (76.5%), 13 (76.5%), and 5 (29.4%) of patients respectively.</p><fig position="float" id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Adverse events. (<bold>A</bold>) Summary of treatment-emergent adverse events and (<bold>B</bold>) treatment-related adverse events by RECIST 1.1 criteria for all patients treated in the expansion cohort of PY159. (<bold>C</bold>) Summary of treatment-emergent adverse events and (<bold>D</bold>) treatment-related adverse events by RECIST 1.1 criteria for all patients treated in the expansion cohort of PY314. RECIST 1.1, Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumor version 1.1.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jitc-13-3-g002.jpg"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2" orientation="portrait"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Summary of SAE and irAE from the PY159 and P314 ovarian cancer cohorts</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">PY159, no. (%)</td><td colspan="2" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">PY314, no. (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune-related adverse events</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All grades</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade ≥3</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All grades</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grade ≥3</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arthralgia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (76)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Stomatitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (29)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Myalgia</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (18)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Arthritis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fatigue</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Hypothyroidism</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Fever</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Decreased appetite</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Dermatitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Erythema</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Immune-mediated dermatitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Diarrhea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" colspan="5" align="left" rowspan="1">Serious adverse events</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pericardial effusion</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)<sup><xref rid="T2_FN1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></sup></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Enterovesical fistula</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Immune-related dermatitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pleuritic chest pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urinary tract infection</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Plural effusion</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (12)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Urinary tract obstruction</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Gastroenteritis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nausea</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Pain</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Acute kidney injury</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (13)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Acute small bowel obstruction</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (19)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (19)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Leukocytosis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Intestinal perforation</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (13)<sup><xref rid="T2_FN1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Septic shock due to UTI</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Takatsubo’s cardiomyopathy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)<xref rid="T2_FN1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>*</sup></xref><sup><xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Acute respiratory failure</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)<sup><xref rid="T2_FN1" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref><xref rid="T2_FN2" ref-type="table-fn">†</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Tonsillitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Nephropathy</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Thrombophlebitis</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> Upper GI hemorrhage</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">–</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (6)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1" fn-type="other"><label>*</label><p>Grade 5., #: These toxicities occurred in the same .</p></fn><fn id="T2_FN2" fn-type="other"><label>†</label><p>These toxicities occurred in the same patient.</p></fn><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>GIgastrointestinalirAEimmune-related adverse eventSAEserious adverse eventUTIurinary tract infection</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3-3-2"><title>PY314</title><p>All 16 (100%) patients experienced at least 1 TEAE of Grade 1 or 2. There were 12 patients (75%) who experienced Grade 3 TEAEs. The most common TEAEs occurring in &gt;15% of patients are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2C</xref> and <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 1</xref>. TRAEs occurred in 9 (56.3%) patients. Grade 1 and 2 TRAEs occurred in 4 (25%) patients and Grade 3 TRAEs occurred in 2 (12.5%) patients. TRAEs occurring in &gt;10% of patients are shown in <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">figure 2D</xref> and <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>. SAEs occurred in 12 (75%) patients, with Grade 1 and 2 events occurring in 3 (18.8%) patients and Grade 3 events occurring in 10 patients (62.5%). There were 2 unrelated fatal adverse events on this study. One patient had a fatal bowel perforation, and another patient developed stress cardiomyopathy and respiratory failure, both felt to be related to underlying disease. <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> summarizes the complete list of SAEs and irAEs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3-4"><title>Pharmacokinetics and exploratory TREM1/2 analysis</title><p>Pharmacokinetic data was available for 11 patients and 9 patients from the TREM1 and TREM2 expansion cohorts, respectively. For patients who received PY159, the mean maximum concentration (C<sub>max</sub>, ± SD) was 78.8 µg/mL±38.9 and the mean time to maximum concentration (T<sub>max</sub>) was 7.92 hours±21.36 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3A</xref><bold>,</bold>
<xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 1</xref>). The half-life was 8.8 days±2.5. For PY314, the mean C<sub>max</sub> (±SD), (T<sub>max</sub>), and t<sub>1/2</sub> were 198 µg/mL±64, 6.72 hours±15.6, and 8.2 days±4.6, respectively (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">figure 3B</xref>, <xref rid="SP1" ref-type="supplementary-material">online supplemental table 2</xref>). No antidrug antibodies to PY159 or PY314 were detected. There was no association between PY159 or PY314 exposure and toxicity or clinical outcomes. No pharmacokinetic data was obtained on patients who crossed over to the pembrolizumab combination arm in both studies.</p><fig position="float" id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Plasma concentration-time profile after (<bold>A</bold>) 3 mg/kg of PY159 and (<bold>B</bold>) 10 mg/kg of PY314.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jitc-13-3-g003.jpg"/></fig><p>The expression of TREM1 and TREM2 was also evaluated in the PY159 and PY314 expansion studies respectively. In PY159, TREM1 expression was available for 9 (52.9%) patients (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>). In 2 patients, TREM1 expression was similar between archival tissue and pre-treatment biopsy. TREM1 expression increased in 2 patients following treatment with PY159. There was no definitive relationship given small numbers between treatment response and TREM1 expression (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>). TREM2 expression was available in 15 (93.8%) patients on the PY314 expansion study (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>). TREM2 expression varied between archival tumor samples and pre-treatment biopsies in all available patients. Three out of 4 (75%) patients with a decrease in post-treatment TREM2 compared with pre-treatment expression had stable disease (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>TREM1/2 expression and best response. Summary of response and TREM1% in pre/post-treatment biopsies in patients from PY159 trial, and summary of response and TREM2% in pre/post-treatment biopsies in patients from PY314 trial. TREM1, triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 1; TREM2, triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 2.</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" position="float" orientation="portrait" xlink:href="jitc-13-3-g004.jpg"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>To our knowledge, this is the first report of targeting tumor infiltrating macrophages (TAMs) in OVCA as an attempt to overcome resistance to immunotherapy in this disease.</p><p>Prior attempts at the use of single agent immunotherapy in platinum-resistant ovarian cancer have had limited effect, likely secondary to the complex interplay between the TME, cancer cells, and infiltrating immune cells. Specifically, it is felt that immunosuppressive myeloid populations within the TME employ a multitude of mechanisms to undermine antitumor immunity and to directly promote tumor growth, even in the setting of immunotherapy use leading to resistance. Combining multiagent drugs to overcome this resistance is likely key, although the best combinations of agents are yet to be determined.<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13 14 25 26</sup></xref> Limited combination therapy trials with reported outcomes with other immunotherapy agents or conventional chemotherapies (mostly in expansion cohorts or phase II although some phase III have occurred), in both platinum sensitive and resistant disease, have yet to demonstrate significant activity, notwithstanding some modest activity. In general, patients in these trials have seen significantly less chemotherapy, on average, than the patients treated in either the PY159 or the PY314 study presented here.<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></p><p>While targeting tumor-associated macrophages is a mechanism that is garnering more interest in OVCA treatment and multiple trials are underway, no trials to date have reported on outcomes in this space (reviewed in Truxova <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>)<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> as many of the agents tested have cross-activity in many aspects of the TME. The contemporary agents PY159 and PY314 have been demonstrated to be more specific myeloid-directed monoclonal antibody therapies, ideally suited to evaluate the therapeutic impact of TAM modulation in OVCA.</p><p>Both PY159 and PY314 achieved adequate plasma concentrations based on the phase Ia data and PK analyses and in the current study and both PY314 and PY159 monotherapy led to a CBR of 50% (best response as noted stable disease) with an acceptable safety profile and overall were well tolerated. While patients were allowed to cross-over on progression to a combination with pembrolizumab, no responses were noted in this arm although a few patients achieved stable disease when crossing over to combination therapy.</p><p>In the exploratory analysis of post-treatment depletion of TREM1/2, patients with SD did appear to have reduced levels of both receptors; however, in this small phase Ia/b study, the number of patients with post-treatment biopsies was too small to confirm association with response to therapy. Our understanding of TREM1 and TREM2 biology continues to evolve. For instance, inhibition of TREM1 via small molecule inhibitors and short interfering RNA suppressed tumor growth and metastasis in a preclinical model of hepatocellular carcinoma.<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> It is conceivable that competing effects of TREM1 agonism on myeloid cells and tumor cells led to the findings in this study. A similar observation has been made in Head and Neck squamous cell carcinoma where TREM2 expression on multinucleated giant macrophages portends a favorable prognosis.<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref> In this situation, TREM2 antagonism could facilitate disease progression. A limitation of our study is the absence of tissue-based pharmacodynamic biomarkers beyond baseline and on-treatment TREM1/2 expression. Identification of immune cell infiltrates, or subset analysis of which TREM2-positive myeloid lineage cells were depleted in patients with stable disease on this study could have yielded information that refined our understanding of TREM1/2 biology in ovarian cancer and potentially guide future combination therapy strategies.</p><p>While this study and its interpretation are limited secondary to a small sample size and a heavily pretreated population, some of whom had received immunotherapy, both PY159 and PY314 were well tolerated and demonstrated reasonable safety profile as single agents and in combination with pembrolizumab. Given the CBR in heavily pretreated platinum-resistant ovarian cancer, these agents warrant additional investigation in combination with IO agents with consideration of scheduling (i.e. up-front inclusion) and with additional targeted and conventional agents in this difficult to treat patient population with limited options.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>supplementary material</title><supplementary-material id="SP1" position="float" content-type="local-data" orientation="portrait"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jitc-2024-010959</object-id><label>online supplemental file 1</label><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="jitc-13-3-s001.docx" id="d67e1295" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We gratefully acknowledge the patients who participated in this study and their families. We thank the clinical research staff and caregivers at all participating sites.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This study was supported by Pionyr Immunotherapeutics. Pionyr immunotherapeutics was acquired by Ikena Oncology in 2023</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not applicable.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> These studies received approval from the Dana Farber/Harvard Cancer Center Institutional Review Board (# 22-015 and 21-599) and the Institutional Review Boards of the respective institutions. All participants gave consent to participate.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Giaquinto</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Cancer statistics, 2024</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2024</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3322/caac.21820</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38230766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Luvero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Milani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ledermann</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Treatment options in recurrent ovarian cancer: latest evidence and clinical potential</article-title><source>Ther Adv Med Oncol</source><year>2014</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1758834014544121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25342990</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4206613</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Slaughter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Primary and acquired platinum-resistance among women with high grade serous ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Gynecol Oncol</source><year>2016</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2016.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27208536</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Naumann</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Management strategies for recurrent platinum-resistant ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Drugs (Abingdon Engl)</source><year>2011</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>1397</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/11591720-000000000-00000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21812505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Angelergues</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Konecny</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Mirvetuximab Soravtansine in FRα-Positive, Platinum-Resistant Ovarian Cancer</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2023</year><volume>389</volume><fpage>2162</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa2309169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38055253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hudry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Le Guellec</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Meignan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Tumor-Infiltrating Lymphocytes (TILs) in Epithelial Ovarian Cancer: Heterogeneity, Prognostic Impact, and Relationship with Immune Checkpoints</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>5332</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers14215332</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36358750</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9656626</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pawłowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rekowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kuryło</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Current Understanding on Why Ovarian Cancer Is Resistant to Immune Checkpoint Inhibitors</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2023</year><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>10859</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms241310859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37446039</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10341806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Vlaeminck</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Maebe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Turn Back the TIMe: Targeting Tumor Infiltrating Myeloid Cells to Revert Cancer Progression</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1977</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.01977</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30233579</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6127274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bingle</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The role of tumour-associated macrophages in tumour progression: implications for new anticancer therapies</article-title><source>J Pathol</source><year>2002</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/path.1027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11857487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cassetta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fragkogianni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sims</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Human Tumor-Associated Macrophage and Monocyte Transcriptional Landscapes Reveal Cancer-Specific Reprogramming, Biomarkers, and Therapeutic Targets</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2019</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>602</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccell.2019.02.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30930117</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6472943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cassetta</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Macrophage targeting: opening new possibilities for cancer immunotherapy</article-title><source>Immunology</source><year>2018</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imm.12976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29963704</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6187207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>De Nola</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Menga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Castegna</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Crowded Crosstalk between Cancer Cells and Stromal Microenvironment in Gynecological Malignancies: Biological Pathways and Therapeutic Implication</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>2401</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20102401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31096567</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6567055</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>DeNardo</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ruffell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Macrophages as regulators of tumour immunity and immunotherapy</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41577-019-0127-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7339861</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Jahchan</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mujal</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Tuning the Tumor Myeloid Microenvironment to Fight Cancer</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>1611</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2019.01611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31402908</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC6673698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dower</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Saraf</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Innate immune responses to TREM-1 activation: overlap, divergence, and positive and negative cross-talk with bacterial lipopolysaccharide</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2008</year><volume>180</volume><fpage>3520</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.180.5.3520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18292579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>McVicar</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>TREM and TREM-like receptors in inflammation and disease</article-title><source>Curr Opin Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2009.01.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19230638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC2723941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mohammed</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>TREM-1 is induced in tumor associated macrophages by cyclo-oxygenase pathway in human non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>e94241</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0094241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24842612</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4026315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>DeVaux</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>The Triggering Receptor Expressed on Myeloid Cells 2 Binds Apolipoprotein E</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2015</year><volume>290</volume><fpage>26033</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M115.677286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26374897</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4646256</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Binnewies</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Targeting TREM2 on tumor-associated macrophages enhances immunotherapy</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2021</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>109844</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2021.109844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34686340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Khantakova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Brioschi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Molgora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><article-title>Exploring the Impact of TREM2 in Tumor-Associated Macrophages</article-title><source>Vaccines (Basel)</source><year>2022</year><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>943</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines10060943</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35746551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9227554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Struckmeier</surname><given-names>A-K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Radermacher</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fehrenz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>TREM2 Is Associated with Advanced Stages and Inferior Prognosis in Oral Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>4635</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/cancers14194635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36230558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9561992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title><italic toggle="yes">TREM2</italic> is associated with tumor immunity and implies poor prognosis in glioma</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2022</year><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>1089266</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.1089266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36713360</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9874686</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Winer</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barve</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A phase 1a dose-escalation study of PY159, a monoclonal antibody targeting TREM1 (triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 1)</article-title><source>JCO</source><year>2023</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>2523</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2023.41.16_suppl.2523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Patnaik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Winer</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A phase 1a dose-escalation study of PY314, a TREM2 (Triggering Receptor Expressed on Macrophages 2) targeting monoclonal antibody</article-title><source>JCO</source><year>2022</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2648</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2022.40.16_suppl.2648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Baci</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bosi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gallazzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>The Ovarian Cancer Tumor Immune Microenvironment (TIME) as Target for Therapy: A Focus on Innate Immunity Cells as Therapeutic Effectors</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>3125</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms21093125</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32354198</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7247443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Truxova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Cibula</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Spisek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Targeting tumor-associated macrophages for successful immunotherapy of ovarian carcinoma</article-title><source>J Immunother Cancer</source><year>2023</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e005968</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jitc-2022-005968</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36822672</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9950980</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Herzog</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hays</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Barlin</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>ARTISTRY-7: phase III trial of nemvaleukin alfa plus pembrolizumab vs chemotherapy for platinum-resistant ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Future Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1577</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fon-2023-0246</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37334673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Hinchcliff</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Knisely</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Adjei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Randomized phase 2 trial of tremelimumab and durvalumab in combination versus sequentially in recurrent platinum-resistant ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2024</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.35126</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38009662</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11267492</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Thaker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Mendivil</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>A phase III, multicenter, randomized study of olvimulogene nanivacirepvec followed by platinum-doublet chemotherapy and bevacizumab compared with platinum-doublet chemotherapy and bevacizumab in women with platinum-resistant/refractory ovarian cancer</article-title><source>Int J Gynecol Cancer</source><year>2023</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1458</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/ijgc-2023-004812</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37666539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Kurtz</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pujade-Lauraine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oaknin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Atezolizumab Combined With Bevacizumab and Platinum-Based Therapy for Platinum-Sensitive Ovarian Cancer: Placebo-Controlled Randomized Phase III ATALANTE/ENGOT-ov29 Trial</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>4768</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.23.00529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37643382</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC10602539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Oza</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy with or without avelumab followed by avelumab maintenance versus chemotherapy alone in patients with previously untreated epithelial ovarian cancer (JAVELIN Ovarian 100): an open-label, randomised, phase 3 trial</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1275</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00342-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34363762</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bookman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Sehouli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Atezolizumab, Bevacizumab, and Chemotherapy for Newly Diagnosed Stage III or IV Ovarian Cancer: Placebo-Controlled Randomized Phase III Trial (IMagyn050/GOG 3015/ENGOT-OV39)</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1842</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.21.00306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33891472</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8189598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Pujade-Lauraine</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ledermann</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Avelumab alone or in combination with chemotherapy versus chemotherapy alone in platinum-resistant or platinum-refractory ovarian cancer (JAVELIN Ovarian 200): an open-label, three-arm, randomised, phase 3 study</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1034</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(21)00216-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34143970</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>O’Malley</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Monk</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Niraparib and dostarlimab for the treatment of recurrent platinum-resistant ovarian cancer: results of a Phase II study (MOONSTONE/GOG-3032)</article-title><source>Gynecol Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>178</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygyno.2023.10.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37890345</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11185194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Yap</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Bardia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Dvorkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Avelumab Plus Talazoparib in Patients With Advanced Solid Tumors: The JAVELIN PARP Medley Nonrandomized Controlled Trial</article-title><source>JAMA Oncol</source><year>2023</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamaoncol.2022.5228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36394849</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9673022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>SX</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>Pharmacological Inhibition or Silencing of TREM1 Restrains HCC Cell Metastasis by Inactivating TLR/PI3K/AKT Signaling</article-title><source>Cell Biochem Biophys</source><year>2024</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>2673</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12013-024-01377-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">38954352</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author">
<name name-style="western"><surname>Gessain</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Anzali</surname><given-names>A-A</given-names></name>
<name name-style="western"><surname>Lerousseau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>
</person-group><article-title>TREM2-Expressing Multinucleated Giant Macrophages Are a Biomarker of Good Prognosis in Head and Neck Squamous Cell Carcinoma</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2352</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-24-0018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39270324</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC11609822</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>All data relevant to the study are included in the article or uploaded as supplementary information.</p></sec></back></article></pmc-articleset>